now big challenge that we face when
we're trying to deal with global crises
is really understanding what it means to
be human and a key piece of the answer
to the question of what is humanity can
be found in this really excellent book
the social conquest of Earth by Edward o
Wilson so yo Wilson is a biologist who
studied ants and social animals in
general and how they form what are
called super organisms where large
numbers of ants form a colony large
numbers of bees form a hive and then
that larger structure the hive or the
colony operates as if it's an organism
itself and so what he does in this book
that's really wonderful is he explains
how human social behavior came into
being now there's a specific technical
term called eusociality as spelled EU
social you social is an organism that is
able to create a social structure that
includes members that are not
necessarily identical twins and that can
have multiple social roles or economic
purposes and can incorporate more than
one generation within that structure so
ants work this way bees wasps termites
and that the only non insect example
that has any real significance is humans
so we humans are you social animals and
we think about it where the most social
organism in the world because not only
do we create complex structures
societies in the ways that ants and bees
and termites do but we do it as mammals
and one thing that's really important to
remember about mammals is that we have
live birth offspring and we have really
strong parent-child emotional bonds set
differently humans have empathy and we
form strong social relationships with
emotional ties and the other social
animals meaning the other you social
insects that have the same traits that
we do in terms of super organism do not
have this feature so what is it that
makes humans so you
so interesting so important how does our
social behavior work and what does that
tell us about how we should organize our
societies moving forward well these
things are explored in an amazing
narrative in this book about how humans
came to be the social animal that we are
and one of the things that I found very
powerful for me was this notion of
multi-level selection which is in
evolution we already know that
individual organisms meaning two males
within a community will compete with
each other for food for sexual partners
and so on but and that's called
individual selection at the same time
there's what's called group selection
which is when there's one group
competing with another group that one
group may have advantageous properties
in when over the other one for a long
time and evolutionary theory there was a
big question whether it was group or
individual and it turns out that it's
both and the combination of more than
one level of selection is what's called
multi-level selection so it turns out
that human beings have a very strong
competitive hierarchy tendencies as
individuals so we strive for status and
wealth we compare ourselves with their
peers and try to do better and so
there's a bit of competition within our
groups but at the same time we compete
as groups and we naturally form groups
so we like to form into tribes those
tribes can be based on sports and the
type of fan that we are or religions or
national identities or hobbies that we
have or many numbers many other things
we're very very good at forming groups
so this book explains all of the parts
of our history all the ways that our
social nature came into being which has
profound in concrete insight into what
it means to really be human with
implications for how we should build our
societies so that they support our
pro-social cooperative nature and help
us to achieve things that are good for
us as a superorganism or in other words
as a global civilization in the 21st
century so if you want to understand
more about human social nature or where
it comes from how it works and the
fascinating story of our evolutionary
history
then pick up this book the social
conquest of birth and you will not be
disappointed